Guide to the International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa records
1956-1989
MS 1600
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.75
(9 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence and subject files documenting the work of the International Defense and Aid Fund in North America.
International Defence and Aid Fund. United States Committee
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kenneth N. Carstens, Executive Director of the North American Committee of IDAF, 1989 and 1992.
Biographical / Historical
The International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa was founded in 1964 to seek peaceful and constructive solutions to the problems created by racial oppression in Southern Africa. It grew out of the ad hoc committees that were formed in Britain and South Africa in 1952 for the purpose of raising funds for legal defense and humanitarian aid for victims of injustice, including political prisoners, banned persons, and their families. A United States committee was established in 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa is a humanitarian organization which has worked consistently for peaceful and constructive solutions to the problems created by racial oppression in Southern Africa. Known in African and U.N. circles as "Defense and Aid" or simply "D&A," the organization was established in 1964. It grew directly out of the ad hoc committees that were formed in both Britain and South Africa in 1952 for the purpose of raising funds for legal defense and humanitarian aid for victims of injustice, including political prisoners, banned persons and their families. A United States committee was established in 1972.
Purpose of Defense and Aid:
The objectives of D&A are:
to provide for the legal defense and rehabilitation of the victims of unjust legislation and oppressive arbitrary procedures in South Africa
to provide humanitarian aid and support for their families and dependents
to keep the conscience of the world alive to the issues at stake through the dissemination of reliable information
The primary concern, expressed in clauses (1) and (2) above, is that the needs of those who are victimized by southern Africa's unjust legal systems be met. This means directing funds for the legal defense of detainees and those charged with political offenses; for education courses and reading material for individuals serving prison sentences; and for material assistance to the "banned", the restricted, the families of political prisoners, and, as far as possible, to the hundreds of thousands of people sent to resettlement camps. Funds are raised for these urgent needs both independently and in cooperation with churches, lawyers and humanitarian organizations. Clause (1) is perhaps the most important because fundraising for legal aid for political prisoners is illegal in South Africa.
The secondary concern, expressed in clause (3), is that the world know the truth about what is happening in Southern Africa and understand the full implications of white minority rule in this area. To this end, regular publications (including pamphlets and newsletters) are produced and distributed at public meetings held by the trustees, sponsors, supporters and staff of D&A.
The general purpose of the Defense and Aid Fund has a dual character humanitarian and political in the sense that it is not possible to act humanely in a dehumanizing situation without such actions having some kind of political consequences. But the raison d'être of the Fund is essentially the humanitarian purpose stated above, though the political consequences which may ensue are generally considered desirable. For example, a clear consequence of the humanitarian aid is to strengthen the resistance by reducing sentences and even saving lives on appeal; by exposing torture of political prisoners; and by caring for dependents left without support.
Extracted from IDAF instructional material.
Anti-apartheid movements; Apartheid; International Defence and Aid Fund. United States Committee; International Defence and Aid Fund
- Original Accession, 1956, 1967, 1971-1989, undated; 9.25 linear feet (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Received from: Kenneth N. Carstens, executive director of the North American Committee of IDAF
  - Correspondence/subject files
    - Anti-Apartheid Movement (London), 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Arca Foundation, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Ashar, Jerilyn, 1982 December (Box 1)
    - Brutus, Dennis, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - By-laws--IDAF/USA, 1972, 1981, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Canada, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - Chicago, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Clause I & II appeals, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Coalition on Southern Africa, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Collins, Canon Lewis John, 1972-1973, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Connections Information Services/Charles River Publishing; financial papers, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Contacts; educational and, church related, 1977-1980, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, general, 1976, 1977 January-Sep, 1978-1984 June, 1984 May-1988 June (Box 1)
    - Cry Freedom film benefits, 1987 (Box 2)
    - DEFA research, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - D&A board meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - D&A lawyers (Canada), 1973 (Box 2)
    - D&A Leslie Rubin correspondence, 1956-1977 (Box 2)
    - D&A news requests, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - D&A walkathon, 1981 May 17 (Box 2)
    - Detroit, correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - Donors over $50, 1976 July-1982 June (Box 2)
    - Donor thank you's, 1982 July-1983 June (Box 2)
    - Donors under $50, 1983 June (Box 2)
    - Donor correspondence, under $50, 1983 July-1984 June (Box 2)
    - Donor thank you's, over $50, 1983 July-1984 June (Box 2)
    - Donor correspondence, under $50, 1984 July-1985 June (Box 2)
    - Donor correspondence, over $50, 1984 July-1985 June (Box 2)
    - Donor correspondence, under $50, 1985 July-1986 June (Box 2)
    - Donor correspondence, $50 and over, 1985 July-1987 June (Box 2)
    - Film series, 1975 Fall (Box 2)
    - Films and slide shows, 1975-1983 (Box 2)
    - Financial statements, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - FOCUS advertising, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
    - FOCUS correspondence, general with London, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - FOCUS correspondence with subscribers, claims for back issues, information requests, 1979-1983 June (Box 2)
    - FOCUS promoters, 1977, 1979 (Box 2)
    - FOCUS subscriber lists, 1982-1983, 1986 (Box 2)
    - FOCUS updating correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
    - Ford Foundation, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Foundations, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising: sample mailings from other organizations, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising letters, fiscal, 1981-1982, undated (Box 2)
    - Fundraising mailings, 1979 November-1981 May (Box 2)
    - Fundraising mailings and information, 1972-1979 (Box 2)
    - Gomes, Peter J., 1979-1985 (Box 3)
    - Gordimer film benefit, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Green, Clifford, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Grenville-Grey, Wilfrid, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
    - Harvard Divinity School, field education program, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Honoraria, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Huddleston benefit, undated (Box 3)
    - Information requests, correspondence, 1977-1983 June, 1984 July-1989 June (Box 3)
    - International sponsors, 1970, undated (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Willard, correspondence, MIT, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Lawyers- IDAF/USA, 1972-1977, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Lawyers' Committee, 1967-1972 (Box 3)
    - Legislators, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Liberation movement, representatives, correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence, Allen Cook, 1979-1981, undated (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence, general, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence, including literature information requests, 1984 July-1985 June (Box 3)
    - London invoices, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence, literature, 1972-1987 (Box 3)
    - London: literature orders, 1982-1989 (Box 3)
    - London: correspondence (excluding literature orders), 1977-1980 (Box 4)
    - London: correspondence--"Save for Phyllis", 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Long purpose letter, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Mandela, Nelson and Winnie, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Mass mailing, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Media people: correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 4)
    - Michigan D&A (Jack Bailey's file), 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - Michigan D&A job and office descriptions and procedures, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Namibia, 1974-1976, 1981 (Box 4)
    - National Information Bureau, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - New York Book Fair, 1982-1987 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters and News Notes, transcripts of, 1981-1984 November (Box 4)
    - Newsletters and News Notes, transcripts of, 1984 December-1986 October (Box 5)
    - Newsletters and News Notes, transcripts of, 1986 November-1988 October (Box 6)
    - Newsletters and News Notes, transcripts of, 1988 November-1989 May (Box 7)
    - Newsletters and News Notes, general files of, 1982-1987, undated (Box 7)
    - News Notes, 1982-1989 (Box 7)
    - Nongovernmental organizations, NGOs, 1972, 1977, 1980, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Pan-Africanist Congress, 1972-1973, undated (Box 7)
    - Prisoner adoption plan, 1980, undated (Box 7)
    - Proposals, drafts of, 1974-1975, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Proposals--xeroxed materials, 1971, 1974, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Publication requests, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
    - Purpose of D&A, undated (Box 7)
    - Qoboza, Percy; articles in The Washington Star, 1980 October (Box 7)
    - "Religion renewal letter", 1984 (Box 7)
    - Resumes, 1973-1974, 1979, undated (Box 7)
    - Rhodesia--Report of work (D&A), 1972 (Box 7)
    - Sanky Perlowin Associates, 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    - Skinner, Margaret, adoption scheme, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - "Soweto and the Uprising of 1976 in South Africa," a collection of slides prepared by D&A (Box 7)
    - Speaking engagements--budget and follow-up, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Staff, 1979-1981 (Box 7)
    - Sponsors, 1972-1980 (Box 7)
    - Trustees, 1972-1982 (Box 7)
    - United Nations: correspondence, 1972-1979 (Box 7)
    - U.S. Congress, 1978-1981 (Box 8)
    - Venture In Mission Diocese of Michigan, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
    - Vertical File Index, 1977-1984 (Box 8)
    - Winter, Colin O'Brien, 1973, undated (Box 8)
    - Winter, Colin, resumes, etc., 1973 (Box 8)
    - Women's Committee, 1981-1988 (Box 8)
    - Women's Committee; financial account, 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - Women's Committee mailings, 1981-1983 (Box 8)
    - Women's Committee speakers, 1981-1983 (Box 8)
    - Zimbabwe, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Zimbabwe; newspaper clippings, 1973-1975, undated (Box 8)
- Additional Material, 1989 February-August; Accession 1993-M-029; 0.5; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1993 Feb
  Received from: Kenneth Carstens, 1992 Nov 6
  - "Southern Africa News Calendar", 1989 February-March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Radio news transcripts, primarily of Voice of America, British Broadcasting Corporation, and Radio South Africa, 1989 February-August (Box 1, Folder 2-8)